<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Xoxzo Official Blog: Empowerment</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/feeds/engineering-event-tech-wokrshopseminar-uncategorized.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://devblog.xoxzo.com/</id><updated>2016-11-07T17:04:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Startup and Developer 4th Meetup</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/startup-and-developer-4th-meetup.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-07T17:04:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-11-07T17:04:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-11-07:startup-and-developer-4th-meetup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This weekend I managed to join a developer meetup in KL. The group,
which started in Telegram now has growing to 1K members and this 4th
meetup managed to draw 100+ attendees. It quite a success for such a
small group in the beginning and the meetup itself was planned on ad-hoc
manner, as a mere discussion in the Telegram group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topics range from big data to devops, docker, saas, introduction to
new programming language (elixir), security and how to get funding for
your startup. To be honest I think the number of topics are too much for
just one day event, forcing all the speakers to cramp up their
presentation and touch the topic only at surface level with very little
time for question and answer session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="img_20161105_101628" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/11/img_20161105_101628.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1764 width="2560" height="1920"}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the interesting talk was from Nawawi Jamili, sharing his
experience in building up Urusniaga.my, a Software as a Service (SaaS)
solution for small business to manage their operation such as recording
sales transaction, generating invoice etc. Their main challenge is to
handle provisioning new site when new customer subscribe to the service.
It has to be handled seamlessly so that once the payment process
complete, the customer has their site ready to login and use. Here,
while the main system being developed in PHP, they have a background
process developed in C running to pick up new entry in database that not
being provisioned yet. It remind me to our approach of implementing
queue system, before we move to django-q.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1778" align="alignnone"
width="1920"]&lt;img alt="img_20161105_135742" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/11/img_20161105_135742.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1778 width="1920" height="2560"} Nawawi Jamili
sharing experience building up Urusniaga.my as SaaS.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1770" align="alignnone"
width="1280"]&lt;img alt="whatsapp-image-2016-11-06-at-2-30-45-pm" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/11/whatsapp-image-2016-11-06-at-2-30-45-pm.jpeg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1770 width="1280" height="960"} A friend of friend,
showing demo of bitcoin payment system he has developed.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all meetup event, the "hallway" session is always the best of
all as it allow us to catch up with old and new friends, listening what
they're up to now and exchanging contact for future.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>