<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Xoxzo Official Blog: Empowerment</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/feeds/engineering-pycon.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://devblog.xoxzo.com/</id><updated>2012-06-12T20:12:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>PyCon APAC 2012</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/pycon-apac-2012.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-06-12T20:12:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-06-12T20:12:00+09:00</updated><author><name>xoxzoblog</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-06-12:pycon-apac-2012.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;PyCon APAC 2012 that was held on June 7th - 9th is over. Attended by all
kinds of people from many parts of the world. It was a lovely and an eye
opening experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="asset-img-link" href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/ff4e8-6a0153916e707f970b0167676601ea970b-pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="IMG00356" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/ff4e8-6a0153916e707f970b0167676601ea970b-pi.jpg" title="IMG00356" /&gt;{.asset
.asset-image .at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b0167676601ea970b
.image-full}&lt;/a&gt;The
Marimore team attended the conference and gave a few talk (lightning
talk included) on various topics. Kamal gave a talk titled Python/Django
for PHP Developers which cause quite a stir among the attendees as two
language should never be discussed in the same room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave a brief talk on HTML5 Polyfills. It is my first talk to a public
audience accompanied by some difficulties with LibreOffice Impress
(which does not seem to want to maximize to full screen). Nevertheless
its quite an experience and there will always be a room for
improvement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="asset-img-link" href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/01c8b-6a0153916e707f970b0176155b84da970c-pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="IMG00358" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/01c8b-6a0153916e707f970b0176155b84da970c-pi.jpg" title="IMG00358" /&gt;{.asset
.asset-image .at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b0176155b84da970c
.image-full}&lt;/a&gt;Most
of the talks are great, but a few that really interest me is Diversity
as a Dependency (Anna Ravenscroft), Relational Database Access with
Python 'sans' ORM (Mark Rees). I've attended Mr Rees's talk on several
occasions, &lt;a href="http://blog.mosc.my/2009/06/testing-web-apps-with-scripting.html"&gt;MOSC
2009&lt;/a&gt;
 and other MyOSS Meetup at Technology Park Malaysia, he's an excellent
speaker and the topic he presents is kind of refreshing in a world where
framework is abundant, going back to its roots, Python DB API. Diversity
as a Dependency touched on a lot of psychological phenomenon on what
makes a group of people outstanding. The barriers that we face in
working as a group such as groupthink, conformity, anchoring and many
more are mentioned and explained in detail by the speaker, Anna
Ravenscroft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the talks are great especially the keynotes, the food is nice
and to top it off, the programming tournament is something that I have
never experienced, as I have never been good at a very time constrained
programming challenge, it was tough, me and several others only managed
to solve 1 question in 10 minutes (1st place answers all 10 questions in
that amount of time). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully on the next PyCon, it could be better with more interesting
topics and speakers, and more food delicious food of course.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>