<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Xoxzo Official Blog: Empowerment</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/</id><updated>2016-11-07T17:04:00+09:00</updated><entry><title>Participating KOF-Kansai Open Source Forum</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/kof-2016-report.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-11-14T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-11-14T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Aiko Yokoyama</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-11-14:en/kof-2016-report.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce that our KOF (Kansai Open Forum held on Nov 11 &amp;amp; 12 in
Osaka, Japan) display ended successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="KOF関西バナー" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/kof-2016/kof.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had many visitor to our booth and were shown demonstration of ‘Sending
SMS/Calls from the Internet’. Some immediately went thinking how to integrate
the API into their own applications, while others tried to work out how this
could work or just simply enjoy what our API does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="KOF関西にてXoxzoのブース" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/kof-2016/kof-booth.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="KOF関西にてXoxzoの野中がLTを行う" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/kof-2016/kof-akira-lt.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a great experience for us meeting our potential users, not only spreading
our technology but also to know what further solutions they are seeking for,
which would raise us to the next step, for further developments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are for sure to come back to the next exhibition to meet more people, with
our aim to empower the world.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kof"></category><category term="osaka"></category><category term="exhibition"></category></entry><entry><title>KOF-関西オープンフォーラムを終えて</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/../ja/kof-2016-report.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-11-14T11:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-11-14T11:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Aiko Yokoyama</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-11-14:en/../ja/kof-2016-report.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="KOF関西バナー" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/kof-2016/kof.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2016年11月11日と12日の両日、KOFー関西オープンフォーラムに出展しました。
訪問者もほとんど切れることなく会場を賑わし、Xoxzoのサービスに興味を持った様々な方とお話をすることができて、とても充実した2日間となりました。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="KOF関西にてXoxzoのブース" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/kof-2016/kof-booth.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="KOF関西にてXoxzoの野中がLTを行う" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/kof-2016/kof-akira-lt.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;頂いたご質問やご要望は、今後の我々の進む道にも活かされて行くことと思います。
ご多忙の中、ご来場いただき、弊社ブースをご訪問いただいた方々、また、特設ステージでの講演にご参加いただいた皆様、誠にありがとうございました。今後ともどうぞよろしくお願いします。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kof"></category><category term="大阪"></category><category term="出展"></category></entry><entry><title>Startup and Developer 4th Meetup</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/startup-and-developer-4th-meetup.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-07T17:04:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-11-07T17:04:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-11-07:en/startup-and-developer-4th-meetup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This weekend I managed to join a developer meetup in KL. The group,
which started in Telegram now has growing to 1K members and this 4th
meetup managed to draw 100+ attendees. It quite a success for such a
small group in the beginning and the meetup itself was planned on ad-hoc
manner, as a mere discussion in the Telegram group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topics range from big data to devops, docker, saas, introduction to
new programming language (elixir), security and how to get funding for
your startup. To be honest I think the number of topics are too much for
just one day event, forcing all the speakers to cramp up their
presentation and touch the topic only at surface level with very little
time for question and answer session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="img_20161105_101628" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/11/img_20161105_101628.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1764 width="2560" height="1920"}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the interesting talk was from Nawawi Jamili, sharing his
experience in building up Urusniaga.my, a Software as a Service (SaaS)
solution for small business to manage their operation such as recording
sales transaction, generating invoice etc. Their main challenge is to
handle provisioning new site when new customer subscribe to the service.
It has to be handled seamlessly so that once the payment process
complete, the customer has their site ready to login and use. Here,
while the main system being developed in PHP, they have a background
process developed in C running to pick up new entry in database that not
being provisioned yet. It remind me to our approach of implementing
queue system, before we move to django-q.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1778" align="alignnone"
width="1920"]&lt;img alt="img_20161105_135742" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/11/img_20161105_135742.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1778 width="1920" height="2560"} Nawawi Jamili
sharing experience building up Urusniaga.my as SaaS.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1770" align="alignnone"
width="1280"]&lt;img alt="whatsapp-image-2016-11-06-at-2-30-45-pm" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/11/whatsapp-image-2016-11-06-at-2-30-45-pm.jpeg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1770 width="1280" height="960"} A friend of friend,
showing demo of bitcoin payment system he has developed.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all meetup event, the "hallway" session is always the best of
all as it allow us to catch up with old and new friends, listening what
they're up to now and exchanging contact for future.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Tokyu Ruby Kaigi</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/tokyu-ruby-kaigi.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-09T10:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-06-09T10:00:00+09:00</updated><author><name>anonaka</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-06-09:en/tokyu-ruby-kaigi.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On May 29, I attended the 10th annual &lt;a href="http://regional.rubykaigi.org/tokyu10/"&gt;Tokyu Ruby
Kaigi&lt;/a&gt; held at Shibuya,Tokyo. I
made a lightning talk about a &lt;a href="https://rubygems.org/gems/xoxzo-cloudruby"&gt;Xoxzo telephony
gem&lt;/a&gt; (gem is the ruby
packaging system). This gem is the first public gem I wrote in my
life. I also enjoyed a lot of exciting talks, laughs and of course
fantastic food and excellent beer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids="1451,1452" type="rectangular"]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second time I joined this conference and hopefully want to
come back next year!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="ruby"></category></entry><entry><title>Malaysia Open Source Conference (MOSCMY) and JomLaunch</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/malaysia-open-source-conference-moscmy-and-jomlaunch.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-03T10:02:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-06-03T10:02:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-06-03:en/malaysia-open-source-conference-moscmy-and-jomlaunch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I've attended one of the biggest open source event in Malaysia
and another co-located event that is JomLaunch by prominent local
developer community called JomWeb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first slot I managed to join (I skipped the first day) is
called &lt;a href="http://lanyrd.com/2016/moscmy2016/sdzpgb/"&gt;Pentaksiran Pengaturcaraan Komputer Berdasarkan Domain-domain
Pembelajaran (Programming Assesment based on Learning
Domains)&lt;/a&gt;by Ms. Noraini
Talib, IT Executive at UKM. How to teach programming is always my topic
of interest and it good to see it from an academic perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="noraini" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/noraini.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1399 width="960" height="1280"}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next talk about usage of &lt;a href="https://obsproject.com/"&gt;Open Broadcaster Software
(OBS)&lt;/a&gt;  for classroom teaching also
interesting. I'd never heard the software before and I can forsee some
good use of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="open-broadcaster" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/open-broadcaster.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1350 width="960" height="1280"}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have my own slot too, which aim to encourage and kickstart people to
become OSS project contributor on Github. It supposed to be a workshop
so my initial plan is to have everyone do a hands on practice but it
turned out nobody brought a laptop so I have to make good use of the 2
hours slot by talking about contributing to open source project. I'd
failed to fully utilize the 2 hours but we have a good discussion with
the participants. A lecturer came up to me at the end of the session
saying she plan to start introducing git/github into her students
project going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="kamal" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/kamal.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1438 width="960" height="1280"}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another slot by Abyres (one of the sponsor) also an eye opening. I
learned about &lt;a href="http://www.mampu.gov.my/DRSA"&gt;Data Raya Sektor Awam
(DRSA)&lt;/a&gt; which is a big data initiative by
government to provide executive framework on how big data project can be
implemented in the government agency. It surprise me that they are
doing Patriotisme Analysis as part of the sentiment analysis project
under Kementerian Komunikasi dan Multimedia Malaysia. They also revealed
their open source project called
&lt;a href="http://pysiphae.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;PySiphae&lt;/a&gt; which
interestingly being developed in Python. They use postgresql a lot and
to the question whether postgres still relevant in post-hadoop world,
their answer is YES, though they advice to target it for reporting, data
warehouse, data mart vs operational db that is currently on proprietary,
which in their own word provide better risk vs reward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real kicker in this conference to me is the slot by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/adzmely"&gt;Adzmely
Mansor&lt;/a&gt; from
&lt;a href="https://blog.nexoprima.com/"&gt;Nexoprima&lt;/a&gt;. All this while, I've only
known him through online channel so it's good to see him in person. Very
soft spoken but fully energetic guy, especially when talking about
highly technical topics. His slot was on &lt;a href="https://www.scribd.com/doc/313886524/Vertical-Performance-Tuning-MOSC2016"&gt;Vertical Performance
Tuning&lt;/a&gt;
of a linux system. It's a topic rarely covered compared to horizontal
scaling. The slot deep dived into the linux system, starting from the
basic stuff of understanding what is system load and OS thread to kernel
hacking on TCP TIME_WAIT to improve network performance. The core theme
of the talk is that little attention is giving to vertical tuning that
usually lead to underused of system resources. This definitely require a
dedicated blog post to cover all the details ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="adzmely" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/adzmely.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1388 width="960" height="1280"}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jenkins is nothing new to us (and it's a long overdue task for us to
incorporate Jenkins or some other CI tools into our workflow) but what
make &lt;a href="http://lanyrd.com/2016/moscmy2016/sdzxqz/"&gt;the talk&lt;/a&gt; interesting
was that it come from a group of student from UiTM Shah Alam. We may
commonly heard how student are lacking off adequate knowledge about what
industry need for real job but these students definitely different,
thanks to their charismatic lecturer who personally set up the group to
provide a platform for the students to explore relevant tech stuff
outside of their academic studies. I have a short chat with the lecturer
and it gave me some ideas how we can set up similar group here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following up after the closing of MOSCMY is JomLaunch on the next day,
an event by different organizer but sharing the same venue. It's a
platform for startup, individual or team to showcase their latest
project or product. Everyone got 10 minutes stage time and 16
projects/products have been showcased these time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stampede's blog has &lt;a href="http://www.stampede-design.com/blog/2016/06/being-all-inspired-at-jomlaunch/"&gt;already covered the event in
detail&lt;/a&gt;
so I don't plan to repeat it here. Head over to their cool blog !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="sumbermanusia" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/06/sumbermanusia.jpg" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-full .wp-image-1381 width="1280" height="718"}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Night mamak session with &lt;a href="http://sumbermanusia.my/"&gt;SumberManusia.my&lt;/a&gt;
team (they also present on JomLaunch). Photo credit to &lt;a href="http://blog.nasrulhazim.com/"&gt;Nasrul
Hazim&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the whole event was very exciting as I managed to meet old and
new friends, some of which all these while we met only in the online
world. Btw, if you missed this event, kindly note that we have another
&lt;a href="https://pycon.my/"&gt;PyconMy&lt;/a&gt; conference coming up in August. Make sure
to grab the ticket while it still available. See you there !&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="open source"></category></entry><entry><title>The communication costs of remote work</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/the-communication-costs-of-remote-work.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-22T23:25:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-04-22T23:25:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-04-22:en/the-communication-costs-of-remote-work.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have a distributed team and everyone remotely works from wherever
they are (6 cities across 3 countries). Remote work is nothing new
(we've practiced it since 2007), at least for us and generally: But it
requires a different approach and similar to re-thinking about &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; as
we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we communicate with another human being face-to-face, the human
brain is a wonderful thing, and it can fully utilize it's senses to
process all the information it gets and slice it down to the gist of
what is being communicated. Most of the time, done right,  you get
understood clearly, action gets taken quickly and stuff gets moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A challenge with remote work is that those senses gets removed and only
goes down to one or two (usually only one). What the brain needs to fill
in between will be filled based on incomplete data, biased data and
assumptions. These incomplete or incorrect data needs to be fixed at
some point or another, and if action was taken based on these data,
those action too needs to be fixed. Fixing takes time and money, so this
is what we call &lt;em&gt;communication costs. &lt;/em&gt;Communication costs when they add
up will be significant, &lt;strong&gt;not only in terms of dollars and cents, but
also the toll it takes on emotional stress.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our setup, there are a few simple steps and insights that we take to
reduce communication costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Think of your ticket summaries like the &amp;lt;TITLE&amp;gt; to be indexed.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like any other modern setup, we use ticketing systems to manage and keep
track of our tasks and work. Special attention needs to be taken on how
you write the summary or the title of the tickets so that it include all
the necessary keywords that includes what the ticket is all about, as
nearly all the time that is all that is shown to you in lists&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bad example that just says "write code". &lt;em&gt;Duuh&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bad-example-jira" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/bad-example-jira.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, you don't need to overdo the summary. Something like this will suffice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="jira-good-example" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/jira-good-example.png" /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A concise and precise summary statements will remove the need for anyone
who is going through your tasks to click on each link to read it's
details, in order to decide if it's something they need to look into. A
single cycle of clicking and reading and moving back will maybe take one
minute, and if you'd spent 5 seconds to add a little more precise
information in your summary, that will save tremendous amount of time
and stress (as moving from one screen to another for different tickets
switches your mind into different contexts and is stressful) for whoever
will be going through your tickets. You'll definitely be popular too, as
&lt;em&gt;no one&lt;/em&gt; hates precise and concise information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Make acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use Slack for internal communication, and Slack is great, but
sometimes you don't know if your request or question is getting the
appropriate attention. This is bad because it's ambiguous. When it's
ambiguous, communication costs kicks in because you'll need to spend
time following it up and read the other person's mind&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great thing about Slack is that it allows you to add &lt;a href="http://www.theverge.com/2015/7/9/8916347/slack-emoji-reactions"&gt;reactions to a
post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ack" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/ack.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives you the ability to acknowledge something, without having to
write things out. A second of clicking on a button will remove that
ambiguity as we can see who clicked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Responses go on the same channel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a simple tip, but it can get out of hand if you don't watch out.
Keeping responses to the questions or requests on the same channel (i.e
questions by email is replied by email) keeps everything of the same
context in the same medium, which helps &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; when you search for it
later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Good teamwork pays for your costs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very effective way to pay for your communication costs is to have good
teamwork. &lt;em&gt;Good teamwork&lt;/em&gt; can mean many things, but if I need to distill
it to one thing, it will be for someone in your team to &lt;em&gt;do the expected
thing in a timely manner, without specific instructions from anyone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means people are autonomously working together towards a common
goal without needing much interaction (thus you have little
communications which can incur costs). This is always desirable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question next then will be: How do you create a team with great
teamwork? This is beyond the scope of this post, but I believe the
basics are &lt;strong&gt;respect&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e I respect this person because she is good at
what she does) and &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; (I trust this person to do the correct
thing at the correct time because she is good).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do acknowledge that face to face interaction is still and will always
be very important for us to develop trust and respect among ourselves.
We are after all social animals with complex understanding of one
another. This is the one big disadvantage of remote working, so we try
lessen the impact of this by having periodical Team Camps, where we
actually get together and spend time doing something together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2015-08-19 21.31.17" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/2015-08-19-21-31-17.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don't assume or guess. Give it a call&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final tip is sort of an anti-pattern, and I practice it as a last
resort. If things start to go out of hand via text (email or chat), I'll
make a call, go voice and clear things out. Going voice has the
advantage of upping the communication tempo, giving it an urgent tone
and you can use nuances and make multiple suggestions faster than you
can type them. But voice is &lt;strong&gt;very disruptive &lt;/strong&gt;as everything else need
to stop to handle it, so we use this sparingly and mostly on
pre-determined schedules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have simple rule to decide if I need to make a call: If I still
haven't understood what the issue is, the current action taken and the
intended outcome after reading a particular thread or ticket twice, and
a question concerning via chat still does not answer my question, then
it is time to make a call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the tips and strategies that we take to reduce
communication costs within our diverse and remote team. All teams are
obviously different, and some might work or may not work for yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for us, we'll keep on looking and trying too.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="costs"></category><category term="nomad"></category><category term="remote"></category><category term="tips"></category></entry><entry><title>Tokyo Team Camp</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/tokyo-team-camp.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-03-07T15:21:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-03-07T15:21:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Zaki Akhmad</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-03-07:en/tokyo-team-camp.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's always people on the other side of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1152" align="aligncenter" width="730"]&lt;img alt="Xoxzo
team and family
members." src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/03/imag0603_burst002.jpg?w=730" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-1152 width="730" height="413"} Xoxzo team and family
members.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's 2016 and we just had our first ever team camp attended by all of
the team members (and also some family members!). Previously, most of
our team camps were attended only from the engineering team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team camp lasted for one week full, or we could say in 5 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1148" align="aligncenter"
width="619"]&lt;img alt="Agile/Scrum presentation on Tokyo Team Camp
2016" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/03/2016-02-15_14-05-00_720-e1457311264540.jpg" /&gt;{.size-full
.wp-image-1148 width="619" height="284"} Agile/Scrum presentation on
Tokyo Team Camp 2016[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On day one, Kamal presented about the use of user story and pseudo code
to capture and identify business requirements. It's interesting for me
to see the higher level perspective instead of directly do the code
part. Being into deep: coding everyday, sometimes made me loosing the
bigger picture. Then after lunch, Kamal shared about agile/scrum method
in software development. I've heard about this agile/scrum thing before
but never get into detail of it. And I also saw how they use post it
with different colors to differentiate between main topic and supporting
topic. The interesting part is how we gonna "implement" this post it
approach since we are 100 % working remotely so we don't have the luxury
of looking at the same board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On day two, Kamal explained the evolution of where to put the business
logic. Starting from the views, models, and service layers. Then in the
afternoon I presented about monitoring log and how to do it
automatically because you don't want to spend your whole afternoon
watching the logs manually right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1133" align="aligncenter"
width="730"]&lt;img alt="Working at Roppongi Hills during Tokyo team
camp." src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/20160217172316-e1457312885255.jpg?w=730" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-1133 width="730" height="402"} Working at Roppongi Hills
during Tokyo team camp.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On day three we went to Roppongi Hills as part of our Japanese
experience. Roppongi Hills is an area in Tokyo which famous for business
district and contemporary architecture. Oh, Google Tokyo office is
located at Roppongi Hills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1155" align="aligncenter" width="730"]&lt;img alt="Tokyo
Subway Route
Map" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/03/screenshot-from-2016-03-07-114920.png?w=730" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-1155 width="730" height="512"} Tokyo Subway Route
Map[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took the Tokyo subway train - Oedo line to go there. Have you ever
seen Tokyo train map? You better see it. At first I imagined this map
just like a spaghetti. Compare to Melboure Metro train network, Tokyo
train network far more complicated. And the subway, is like very deep
underground. I didn't remember how many elevators we should take to
reach the surface from Roppongi Subway Station. It's like we're deep 10
metres under the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1135" align="aligncenter"
width="670"]&lt;img alt="Visiting Tokyo Metro Underground Discharge
Channel" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/imag0594-e1457311376693.jpg?w=670" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-1135 width="670" height="1024"} Visiting Tokyo Metro
Underground Discharge Channel[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On day four, Aiko joined us. We went to &lt;a href="http://www.ktr.mlit.go.jp/edogawa/gaikaku/english/"&gt;Greater Tokyo Metro Underground
Discharge Channel&lt;/a&gt;.
We saw how the Japanese built giant tunnel to prevent an area from
flood. It's amazing how to see how Japanese built this mega structures
to prevent flood and saving lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1137" align="aligncenter"
width="730"]&lt;img alt="Visiting Tokyo Mint where Japanese Yen coins are
made." src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/imag0601_burst002.jpg?w=730" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-1137 width="730" height="413"} Visiting Tokyo Mint where
Japanese Yen coins are made.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch, we went to &lt;a href="http://www.mint.go.jp/category/eng"&gt;Japan
Mint&lt;/a&gt;. Japan Mint is a Government
Agency which one of the main tasks is producing JPY coins. Here we saw
how the Japanese coins were made. They also displayed the history of
Japanese coins and special coins for special events such as Olympic
Games, special coins for each of 47 Japanese prefectures and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1151" align="aligncenter"
width="730"]&lt;img alt="Earthquake simulation at Ikebukuro Life Safety Learning
Center" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/03/great_east_japan_earthq_1024-e1457311301799.jpg?w=730" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-1151 width="730" height="358"} Earthquake simulation at
Ikebukuro Life Safety Learning Center[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On day five, we went to Ikebukuro local fire department office. This
fire department office has learning center for visitor. At first, we
learned how to properly use fire suppression. For most of us fire
extinguisher is a common thing but it was my first time pull the pin and
blast the fire extinguisher. After that, we practised how to safely
escape from smoke and use the staircase. Still in the visitor center, we
were having earthquake simulation. Japan is located in an area where
earthquakes are very often happened. Before we ended our visit, we
watched 10-minutes animation video which tells the history of
earthquakes in Japan and how we should face the earthquakes: helping
each others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the period of the camp, we also went through presentations on
internal processes, new services we plan to release and also refresher
presentations on how we're building our current services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_1158" align="aligncenter" width="730"]&lt;img alt="Team
dinner at Japanese
restaurant" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/03/imag0612.jpg?w=730" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-1158 width="730" height="413"} Team dinner at Japanese
restaurant[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, to close our team camp, we had our team dinner at
Japanese restaurant. But unfortunately we missed the karaoke part. After
all, it was an amazing week: working and spending time with your
colleagues and their families.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="team camp"></category><category term="tokyo"></category></entry><entry><title>A python basic class in Tokyo Feb 6, 2016</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/a-python-basic-class-in-tokyo-feb-6-2016.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-15T09:18:00+09:00</published><updated>2016-02-15T09:18:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Aiko Yokoyama</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2016-02-15:en/a-python-basic-class-in-tokyo-feb-6-2016.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://djangogirls.org/"&gt;&lt;img alt="logo" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2016/02/logo.png?w=150" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have attended an event of Django Girls Japan and Python ladies, a
Python basic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://djangogirls-org.connpass.com/event/25660/"&gt;http://djangogirls-org.connpass.com/event/25660/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. An introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We had 8 girls attended with 1 instructor and 3 mentors.&lt;br /&gt;
6 students from within Tokyo and 1 from Nagoya and me from Kyoto.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2. Session&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Using a text book of &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/4797371595"&gt;http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/4797371595&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pre-read a half of the text before arrival, brought in some questions
about. As most of us were really beginners at Python, (0 - 2 years) none
of us really had good knowledge to even make questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructor thinks the basic level that he wanted us to have today is
to have an 'idea' of python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gave us some time to think about:&lt;br /&gt;
- What is Data types, what will be problems if mis-treat the data
types.&lt;br /&gt;
- What is Collection type data, and what are list, dictionary and taple,
their data rules and how to define.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also,&lt;br /&gt;
- What is Functions, what is Argument and what is returned value exactly
mean.&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I had some rough or general idea about them but as he explained as&lt;br /&gt;
Function is like a factory&lt;br /&gt;
Argument is like a reception that would take the orders/materials&lt;br /&gt;
Return value is like a completed product made at the factory&lt;br /&gt;
was very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also then we students wondered what is modules then, so we challenged
onto some exercise to see what it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;exercise 1&lt;br /&gt;
a. Use 'For' and create a program that shows from 1 to 100&lt;br /&gt;
b. Use 'if' to edit that program to show the numbers only over 30&lt;br /&gt;
c. Edit that program to show only even numbers&lt;br /&gt;
d. Edit that program to show only even numbers/over 50&lt;br /&gt;
e. Edit that program to show only odd numbers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;exercise 2&lt;br /&gt;
Create a game program that we can play paper-scissors and rock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I compared my codes with the instructor's, I felt mine is like a
kinder-child made ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;#-*- coding: utf-8&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;## まず、モジュールを読んでくる##&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;## randomモジュールにある、randint()という関数を使う##&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;じゃんけんをしましょう！&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;グー、&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;チョキ、&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;パー&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;##　両者の手をみる ##&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="n"&gt;cpu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;randint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="n"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;input&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;## 勝ち負けの判定 ##&lt;br /&gt;
if user == 1:&lt;br /&gt;
if cpu == 1:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはグー、CPUもグー、「あいこ」です！")&lt;br /&gt;
if cpu == 2:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはグー、CPUはチョキ、あなたの勝ちです！")&lt;br /&gt;
else:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはグー、CPUはパー、あなたの負けです！")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if user == 2:&lt;br /&gt;
if cpu == 1:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはチョキ、CPUはグー、あなたの負けです！")&lt;br /&gt;
if cpu == 2:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはチョキ、CPUもチョキ、「あいこ」です！")&lt;br /&gt;
else:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはチョキ、CPUはパー、あなたの勝ちです！")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if user == 3:&lt;br /&gt;
if cpu == 1:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはパー、CPUはグー、あなたの勝ちです！")&lt;br /&gt;
if cpu == 2:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはパー、CPUはチョキ、あなたの負けです！")&lt;br /&gt;
else:&lt;br /&gt;
print ("あなたはパー、CPUもパー、「あいこ」です！")&lt;br /&gt;
But, anyways, this is the start of learning. I am glad that I have made
a first step.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>Github: Managing fork and making pull request</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/github-managing-fork-and-making-pull-request.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-10T09:08:00+09:00</published><updated>2015-09-10T09:08:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2015-09-10:en/github-managing-fork-and-making-pull-request.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's common when you're using a third party library, there's come a
point when you need to make some changes to accomodate your project
requirements. On Github, it easy to fork the repository into your own
repo and start making all the changes you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to consider when creating a fork is that you always want your
changes to be merged back with the upstream repo. This will lift out lot
of burden in maintaining your changes and syncing it out with the
changes in the upstream. To facilitate this, you have to do a number of
things that will help this 'merging' process easier both on your part
and also original developer(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always create a specific branch for the specific changes you want to
made. This will help in sending a pull request back as it would allow
the original developer(s) to review the changes atomically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the first rule above, it mean changes you did would span into
more than 1 branch, so how would you use that in your project ? So you
need to create another branch, called it develop or something and merge
all the changes in other branches into this branch. So you would
probably have list of branches such as:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;* develop
master
remotes/origin/HEAD -&amp;gt; origin/master
remotes/origin/develop
remotes/origin/master
remotes/origin/signup-form-mixin
remotes/origin/update-email-verify
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Any changes that specific to your project need and never intended to be
merged with upstream repo should be in &lt;code&gt;develop&lt;/code&gt; branch. Never make any
changes to the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch. That branch should only be the place
where you pull changes from upstream.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="git"></category><category term="github"></category><category term="version control"></category></entry><entry><title>PyCon AU 2015 Write Up</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/pycon-au-2015-write-up.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-29T10:33:00+09:00</published><updated>2015-08-29T10:33:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Zaki Akhmad</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2015-08-29:en/pycon-au-2015-write-up.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_666" align="aligncenter" width="630"]&lt;img alt="PyCon
AU 2015 with 440
attendees." src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/img_6546.jpg?w=630" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-666 width="630" height="176"} PyCon AU 2015 with 440
attendees.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's 2015, and it's another time for PyCon Australia. Last year, PyCon
Australia 2014 was held also in Brisbane, Queensland. The same city as
PyCon 2015. Every two years, the same city will host PyCon Australia. In
2016 and 2017, PyCon Australia will be held in Melbourne, Victoria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, there were 440 people who registered. On Friday, the
committee decided to push back the schedules (until before lunch) to 20
minutes because of &lt;em&gt;hiccup&lt;/em&gt; during registration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference was held at Pullman Brisbane - King George Square. The
location is at the heart of Brisbane city. This makes it very
accessible. It only took me only 10 minutes to King George Square from
Herston Bus Station, the closest bus station from where I stayed. One
disadvantage of having a conference at this venue is that basically they
don't have a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; conference room, instead they have multiple rooms
with partition on each side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_658" align="aligncenter"
width="630"]&lt;img alt="Pullman Brisbane - King George Square, the PyCon AU 2015
venue." src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/img_6641.jpg?w=630" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-658 width="630" height="473"} Pullman Brisbane - King George
Square, the PyCon AU 2015 venue.[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://2015.pycon-au.org/programme/about"&gt;conference&lt;/a&gt; took 5 days.
One day for miniconf, two days for the conference, and another two days
for sprints (and also one day for
&lt;a href="http://2015.pycon-au.org/programme/workshops"&gt;workshop!&lt;/a&gt;). Wow, there's
a lot of talks and talks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing the most difficult that I faced with multi-tracks conference
is deciding which talk I should attend. Even though I knew that all &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/PyConAU"&gt;the
talks are recorded&lt;/a&gt;, making this
decision still not easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLs4CJRBY5F1LvjmMRjvSUnGJCWGvhRxtI"&gt;two
keynotes&lt;/a&gt;
at PyCon AU 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gaFk0Sya_HI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://2015.pycon-au.org/media/news/38"&gt;The first keynote speech&lt;/a&gt; is
mainly about Education. It turns out that Israel government has
programming curriculum at very early stage. The speaker told how great
is &lt;a href="https://scratch.mit.edu/"&gt;Scratch&lt;/a&gt; programming language as graphical
programming language but then the difficulties come when we need to
switch to text-based programming language. And Python still the best
choice to teach children in programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NheE6udjfGI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://2015.pycon-au.org/media/news/37"&gt;The second keynote&lt;/a&gt; mainly
about ethical side of programming consequences. In one example, she
showed how Flickr auto tag feature identify a black people as an animal.
In another example she told how someone's Facebook account keeps
repeating a moment when her child is dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically these are following tracks at PyCon AU:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLs4CJRBY5F1LZECyoAZWhWkaJpF5NHQZW"&gt;OpenStack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLs4CJRBY5F1IvHnT3OvHOB49laSsULy_V"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLs4CJRBY5F1IZYVBLXGX1DRYXHMjUjG8k"&gt;Science and
    Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLs4CJRBY5F1I5vuApyUXp6bLWly1E-b0s"&gt;Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put my main interest to these streams: Django, Science and Data, and
Education. So, I switched back from one talk to another talk which are
interests me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1ABPQyANid0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since, I feel that I should learn more about how doing development with
Django web framework, I attended this talk. During this talk, "Two
Scoops of Django" was mentioned a lot. Then about &lt;a href="http://12factor.net/"&gt;12 factor app
manifesto&lt;/a&gt;. Basically this talk was interesting
because it gave you the tips and tricks while doing development with
Django.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k7hSD_-gWMw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the Science and Data stream, this talk interests me a lot. Because
basically this talk gave practical implementation in real life, how we
can predict a sports game result. This talk realizes me that it will be
better for me if I have a good foundation on machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that, there were job board and lightning talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_663" align="aligncenter" width="630"]&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/img_6567.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon
AU 2015 Job
Board" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/img_6567.jpg?w=630" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-663 width="630"
height="473"}&lt;/a&gt;
PyCon AU 2015 Job Board[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_662" align="aligncenter"
width="630"]&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/img_6573.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Interested giving lightning talk? Write it on the
card!" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/img_6573.jpg?w=630" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-662 width="630"
height="473"}&lt;/a&gt;
Interested giving lightning talk? Write it on the card![/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the workshop, I attended electronics workshop instead of Django
Girls workshop. I played with Arduino. I code using Python and made the
blinking LEDs. This electronic workshop was very interesting for me
since we could program Arduino with Python. Back on the days when I was
at university, I should code using assembler to program a
microcontroller. With Python as high level programming language, of
course it will be easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[caption id="attachment_657" align="aligncenter"
width="630"]&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/img_6684.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Electronics workshop at PyCon AU
2015" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/img_6684.jpg?w=630" /&gt;{.size-large
.wp-image-657 width="630"
height="473"}&lt;/a&gt;
Electronics workshop at PyCon AU 2015[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was my first time PyCon AU experience. And it was very nice to meet
people who shares the same interest and enthusiast with you. And in the
end, the main point of attending a conference is to meet its people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you at the next (nearest) PyCon!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="django"></category><category term="PyCon"></category><category term="PyCon AU"></category><category term="PyCon AU 2015"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>PyconMY 2015 Talk - Mastering Python Ecosystem</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/pyconmy-2015-talk-mastering-python-ecosystem.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-28T17:04:00+09:00</published><updated>2015-08-28T17:04:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2015-08-28:en/pyconmy-2015-talk-mastering-python-ecosystem.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Pycon Malaysia (PyconMY) 2015 just wrapped up last week. This is the
first ever Python conference in Malaysia after a &lt;a href="http://Kamal%20Mustafa.github.io/posts/mini-pycon-my-2014.html"&gt;mini
Pycon&lt;/a&gt;
held last year. It was held in Universiti Malaya (UM), Kuala Lumpur.
Unfortunately, due to some emergency with my family, I have to leave
early after delivering my talk and basically missed the whole event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/pycon1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="pycon1" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/pycon1.jpg?w=300" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-medium .wp-image-739 width="300"
height="169"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/pycon2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="pycon2" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/pycon2.jpg?w=300" /&gt;{.alignnone
.size-medium .wp-image-740 width="300"
height="169"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the talk, I try to give broad general overview of what they
can expect if they were some day decide to adopt Python into their work
environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main barrier to Python is not the language itself but the ecosystem
around it. Some people come to Python not because they want to learn it
but because the application they want to use happened to be developed in
Python. If they can get pass this stage, Python would appear as
attractive to them and will make them start learning the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is basically the path that I took to learn Python. I started not by
learning the language, but trying all sort of applications built in
Python. This, I think allow me to begin with an end in mind. Rather than
wondering what I can do with the language once I know all the syntax and
so on, I know exactly what sort of applications Python can build, now I
just need to dig deeper how exactly does people built it. The is how I
managed to see how Python features such as list comprehension,
decorator, metaclass and others being used to solve real problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can view the slides
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Mt6laaDXGWLN7rm1pvYcqeEzCi9FoJ6VLEMryBEMw_c/edit#slide=id.p"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="PyCon"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="talk"></category></entry><entry><title>Django Girls One Day Workshop in Tokyo</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/django-girls-one-day-workshop-in-tokyo.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-06T14:17:00+09:00</published><updated>2015-08-06T14:17:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Aiko Yokoyama</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2015-08-06:en/django-girls-one-day-workshop-in-tokyo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://djangogirls.org/tokyo/"&gt;&lt;img alt="logo_django" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/logo_django.png?w=300" /&gt;{.aligncenter
.size-medium .wp-image-503 width="300"
height="102"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://djangogirls.org/tokyo/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day work shop at TECH LAB PAAK in Tokyo, July 26, 2015&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Django Girls in Tokyo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/20278115621_c87c785323_z.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="20278115621_c87c785323_z" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/20278115621_c87c785323_z.jpg?w=300" /&gt;{.aligncenter
.size-medium .wp-image-505 width="300"
height="225"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a Django workshop for female who wants to start Django. The
participants were not asked any background knowledge in programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were about 30 girls in various age joined with their own laptops.
1 – 2 tutors and mentors are to look after 2 – 3 girls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 am, After a quick introduction, all just showed their great
concentration to work on the &lt;a href="https://www.gitbook.com/book/djangogirlsjapan/workshop_tutorialjp/details"&gt;tutorials
provided&lt;/a&gt;
till the end of the day at 5.30 pm. There was some social meet up after
the workshop, sadly I couldn’t attend that for the distance of my
residence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team of tutor and we pupils, have gone very well together. Basically
we all read the tutorial and proceeded on the little tasks in it by our
own, but every time when I look up high at the ceiling with my hand
rubbing my chin, the tutor flew to me to look my screen over my shoulder
from behind me. He gave me a pin-point advice how to proceed. I felt
easy to ask questions for his friendly atmosphere too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contents of the tutorial&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/19649557504_a990e81024_z.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="19649557504_a990e81024_z" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/19649557504_a990e81024_z.jpg?w=300" /&gt;{.alignright
.size-medium .wp-image-512 width="300"
height="169"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started off with the command line. As I’m getting aged and my first
    experience with computer was before the Windows has come out, so I
    didn’t have any allergy to using the command line but felt like
    meeting the old friend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We installed Python, then Code editor, I was recommended to use
    ATOM.　I liked using ATOM with its nice user-cared features although
    I just started using it. We had a little play using python on the
    command line before starting Django.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created the own directory to work on this project, then installed
    Django==1.8&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We started blog app, then started to modify the blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What we have achieved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/19651250533_d6a200f1a2_z.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="19651250533_d6a200f1a2_z" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/19651250533_d6a200f1a2_z.jpg?w=300" /&gt;{.alignleft
.wp-image-511 .size-medium width="300"
height="169"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the Blog app, we all work to reach our aim of the day, ‘to create
the first web application.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the web surface and database connection/setting up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Django well to create the log-in form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a super-user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try posting the blog contents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List them up then sort them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use HTML and CSS to add nice finishing touch for the cooler-looking
    display&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tried to see how our web looks like, by using the prompt command of
python manage.py runserver but didn’t get to ‘deploy’ though it is in
the tutorial, I myself want to try that in the near future by reviewing
what I have learnt there in a kind of hurry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/20263896922_76dc83048c_z.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="20263896922_76dc83048c_z" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/20263896922_76dc83048c_z.jpg?w=630" /&gt;{.aligncenter
.size-large .wp-image-506 width="630"
height="354"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking at the future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I have got to stand at the start of something new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked doing this kind of thing, I loved to use MS access to create
some small useful application when I was much younger and love touching
HTML/CSS a little bit, but just have been away from doing it as I had no
chance to be involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone gave me this tutorial book, I wouldn’t get this much of
feeling by just reading it, the hands on workshop is a big hooray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now my next task is to review the tutorial myself, and hope to get
deploy before I come back to show off everyone what I really achieved. I
know that that is still just a start of my Django footpath even I get to
it…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never never started, never never go forward. I have at least started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all the Django Girls, the coaches/mentors of the workshop and
the sponsors!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/20263894682_61d9ee050e_z.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="20263894682_61d9ee050e_z" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/20263894682_61d9ee050e_z.jpg?w=300" /&gt;{.alignleft
.size-medium .wp-image-507 width="300"
height="169"}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/20084176790_f05a18a29e_z.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="20084176790_f05a18a29e_z" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/20084176790_f05a18a29e_z.jpg?w=300" /&gt;{.aligncenter
.size-medium .wp-image-508 width="300"
height="215"}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the lunch and tea time sweets provided on the day was beautiful
too! I enjoyed that part of the workshop as well.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="djangogirls"></category><category term="東京"></category></entry><entry><title>Talk at UTHM</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/talk-at-uthm.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-29T09:19:00+09:00</published><updated>2015-05-29T09:19:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2015-05-29:en/talk-at-uthm.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Header image" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/imBJVxY.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days ago, I was invited by Universiti Tun Hussein Onn (UTHM) student
to give a talk on their 1 day seminar for the students in the Computer
Science and Information Technology (FSKTM) faculty. Thinking that this
is a good chance to connect with the students, I'd agreed and went there
with a friend from &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/jomwebjohor/"&gt;JomWeb Johor&lt;/a&gt;, 
a community of web developers in Johor Bahru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not fully prepare, due to short notice I got but I try my best to
share something that I have learnt throughout my careers in this
industry. The title of my talk was '&lt;em&gt;Menjana Pengalaman Melalui OSS
Development&lt;/em&gt;', loosely translated as '&lt;em&gt;Building Experiences through OSS
Development&lt;/em&gt;'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the two and half hours talk, I try to give some insight to
the student on how to solve the most common dilemma of any fresh
graduate (not just in IT) that is - the requirement for x years of
experiences that the industry need. We in IT however are quite lucky
that the same dilemma not necessarily applied to us, if we know how to
get around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the talk, we continued with a forum session joined by 4 other
speakers invited by the organizer. The 4 talk basically run in parallel
in separate rooms, so it quite a miss that I can't listen to the other
sessions. The issues raised in the forum are quite common - is student
prepared as expected by industry, what else can university can do to
equip student, salary, what technologies having the brightest future
etc. But there's one question from a student that I think, caught
everyone in surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This student, basically already spent 4 years in the industry before
deciding to back into university to further his study. He said that he
feel's trapped into his job and passion in programming, not having a
quality life anymore. This is something to ponder I think. Unfortunately
I didn't (other panels as well) has clear answer for him.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="open source"></category><category term="oss"></category><category term="talk"></category></entry><entry><title>AWS Summit KL 2015</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/aws-summit-kl-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-28T23:07:00+09:00</published><updated>2015-05-28T23:07:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Abdul Rahman</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2015-05-28:en/aws-summit-kl-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On the 21st of May, the first AWS Summit was held at Connexion@Nexus,
located in Kuala Lumpur. A total of 1075 participants turned up that day
which lasted from 7.30am till 6pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="IMAG0509" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/5c468-6a0153916e707f970b01b8d11b4dc4970c-pi.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The summit was split into two tracks. The first track is Introduction to
AWS while the second track is AWS Architecture. There were also
exhibition booths ran by sponsors of the event. A good part of the
exhibition was aimed at companies thinking about converting their system
to the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote introduced a new AWS feature called AWS Lambda, which was
the core of several keynotes during the day. Other AWS components were
re-introduced and have their uses featured in several applications. The
keynotes in the advanced track mostly feature big data analytics while
the introduction track introduces the audience to the various services
that AWS has. There is also a dedicated talk about container computing,
mostly referencing to Docker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="IMAG0517" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/12fb2-6a0153916e707f970b01bb0835babb970d-pi.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS Lambda features a serverless and stateless web app. All you need are
functions and make use of S3 and DynamoDB without the need to set up
your own infrastructure. Charges will occur every 100ms the process is
running after the free monthly quota is used up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other services which were highlighted was AWS Machine Learning for
analyzing data trends and predicting outcomes based on the data fed, AWS
Kinesis for live streaming data, AWS Redshift is another kind of
database which is used in big data analytics. Also featured was the
elastic file system, or AWS EFS as well as AWS EMR, which is the
equivalent of the Hadoop cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day ended with a lucky draw session contributed by the sponsors as
well as from AWS themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it was a fun and informative day for all who attended.
The excitement of Lambda still echoed in various conversations long
after the morning keynote and demo was addressed. There is also a
growing support of local services to help other companies migrate to the
cloud. This year's summit seems to be the first step for many Malaysian
companies. But by next year's summit we're definitely going to see even
more creative use out of AWS as more and more people will be exposed and
using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="IMAG0522" src="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/images/6ebd8-6a0153916e707f970b01b8d11b4f16970c-pi.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P/S: This little selfie booth in the outside foyer really grabbed
everyone's attention.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>MARIMORE Engineering Team Camp in Malacca</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/marimore-engineering-team-camp-in-malacca.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-13T14:32:00+09:00</published><updated>2014-09-13T14:32:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Iqbal Abdullah</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2014-09-13:en/marimore-engineering-team-camp-in-malacca.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;Early
September 2014 we had a 2-day team camp for our engineering team in
Malacca.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;Because
all of us work remotely all the time and we usually only communicate via
voice, video and/or text, it is great to meetup and discuss targets,
issues and ideas face-to-face. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;Meetups
are a great way to communicate issues or ideas which are complicated to
be put to paper. I find that discussing ideas are much more effective
face-to-face; Perhaps due to the many tools (like pen and paper)
expressions (nuances in the facial expression, hand movements and voice)
that we can utilize and the real-time nature of the discussion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;At the
same time the beauty of working remotely all the time is that it trains
you to be precise and concise as much as possible but without leaving
too much information out to get your point across. Usually we only have
one shot to communicate (i.e sending an email or a text message) which
if we miss to get the point across, will require the reader to get our
subsequent explaination in her next iteration, and this will require us
to wait.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;The
camp this time was done at &lt;a href="http://www.hattenhotel-melaka.com/"&gt;Hatten Hotel
Malacca&lt;/a&gt;, in the UNESCO heritage
city of &lt;a class="zem_slink" href="http://maps.google.com/maps?ll=2.20569166667,102.256136111&amp;amp;spn=0.1,0.1&amp;amp;q=2.20569166667,102.256136111%20(Malacca%20City)&amp;amp;t=h" title="Malacca City"&gt;Malacca
City&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;
&lt;a class="asset-img-link" href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/afd30-6a0153916e707f970b01b7c6df2ddd970b-pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="2014-09-04
07.42.40" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/afd30-6a0153916e707f970b01b7c6df2ddd970b-pi.jpg?w=300" title="2014-09-04 07.42.40" /&gt;{.asset
.asset-image .at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b01b7c6df2ddd970b
.img-responsive}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;^The\ view\ from\ my\ room^ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;Team
camp started at 10AM on the first day, and since everyone was driving to
the hotel, we met up at the 12th floor executive check-in lounge.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;It was
our first time having our team camp at Hatten Hotel, but we were very
happy with the service. Since we had the executive rooms, we were able
to take advantage of the executive lounge with it's free flow of coffee
and juice, with some light snacks around 4PM in the afternoon.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;The
hotel WiFi was also available and pretty fast, although it was a bit
flaky at times. Each of us has a &lt;a href="http://www.yes.my/v3/personal/devices/huddle.do"&gt;YES 4G
Huddle&lt;/a&gt;, so we managed
to get connected (coverage wasn't an issue since Hatten is in the middle
of the town) when the hotel WiFi was difficult to connect.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;Food
wasn't an issue: There were many small eateries across the street in the
Dataran Pahlawan mall, and for breakfast Hatten had a breakfast plan
included with our reservation and the spread was impressive. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;The
team camp this time focused more on FullCourt, the Cloud Communications
platform &lt;a href="http://press.marimore.co.jp/2014/07/marimore-acquiring-fullcourt.html" title="MARIMORE acquiring FullCourt"&gt;we acquired last
July&lt;/a&gt;.
Discussion focused on the current status of development,
functionalities, issues faced and also an overview of the roadmap that
we have planned for all of our cloud services.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;This
meetup was also to congratulate and welcome &lt;a href="http://www.marimore.co.jp/en/ourstaff/"&gt;Aman, the new addition to
our team&lt;/a&gt;. Aman in mainly
responsible for the technology transfer of FullCourt from the current
FullCourt team.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;&lt;a class="asset-img-link" href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/24e92-6a0153916e707f970b01b8d0692672970c-pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="2014-09-04
12.12.07" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2014/09/24e92-6a0153916e707f970b01b8d0692672970c-pi.jpg?w=300" title="2014-09-04 12.12.07" /&gt;{.asset
.asset-image .at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b01b8d0692672970c
.img-responsive}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;^The\ engineering\ team^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;We
continued our discussion in the morning of the 2nd day, and we ended the
team camp by lunch time since we wanted everyone to be home by
dinner.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
style="font-family:arial, helvetica, sans-serif;font-size:10pt;"&gt;MARIMORE
tries to do team camps a few times a year, and this time it was the
first time we had it in Malacca. I was pretty happy with the experience,
and will put Malacca high on top of our list.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related articles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="zemanta-article-ul zemanta-article-ul-image"
style="margin:0;padding:0;overflow:hidden;"&gt;

&lt;div class="zemanta-article-ul-li-image zemanta-article-ul-li"
style="padding:0;background:none;list-style:none;display:block;float:left;vertical-align:top;text-align:left;width:84px;font-size:11px;margin:2px 10px 10px 2px;"&gt;

[![](http://i.zemanta.com/282082733_80_80.jpg)](http://press.marimore.co.jp/2014/07/marimore-acquiring-fullcourt.html)[MARIMORE
acquiring
FullCourt](http://press.marimore.co.jp/2014/07/marimore-acquiring-fullcourt.html)

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="hatten hotel"></category><category term="malacca"></category><category term="MARIMORE"></category></entry><entry><title>Verify SPF using PySPF module</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/verify-spf-using-pyspf-module.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-03T06:34:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-12-03T06:34:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-12-03:en/verify-spf-using-pyspf-module.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We deals with email a lot and one thing with handling email is to verify
where&lt;br /&gt;
it come from. We must make sure when we receive email from
someone@gmail.com,&lt;br /&gt;
it really was sent from gmail.com server, not from someone else email
server. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sender_Policy_Framework"&gt;SPF or Sender Policy
Framework&lt;/a&gt; is
what being used for that. For all our&lt;br /&gt;
apps, we used &lt;code&gt;libspf&lt;/code&gt; which we wrapped into a convenience python
extension&lt;br /&gt;
that can be used across projects. As time goes by, we want to start&lt;br /&gt;
depreciating all our C code and move everything (hopefully) to Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a Python module called &lt;code&gt;pyspf&lt;/code&gt;. It look like what we're looking
for&lt;br /&gt;
although the documentation seem to suggest that it part of bigger module
called&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;pymilter&lt;/code&gt;. I can't find any documentation showing how to use only the
SPF&lt;br /&gt;
checking utility (if it has one) and after digging through the &lt;a href="http://pymilter.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/pymilter/pyspf/spf.py?view=markup"&gt;source
code&lt;/a&gt;,
I&lt;br /&gt;
found out the function that we need. It exists as &lt;code&gt;spf.check2()&lt;/code&gt;
function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use &lt;code&gt;pyspf&lt;/code&gt; we also need it dependency which called &lt;code&gt;pydns&lt;/code&gt;.
The&lt;br /&gt;
following command should cover us well:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;easy_install pyspf
easy_install pydns
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The module then available for import under the name &lt;code&gt;spf&lt;/code&gt;. You can
import it&lt;br /&gt;
like below:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;spf&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The function signature for &lt;code&gt;spf.check2&lt;/code&gt; function look like this:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;def check2(i, s, h, local=None, receiver=None):
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; for ip address, &lt;code&gt;s&lt;/code&gt; for the sender email address, and &lt;code&gt;h&lt;/code&gt; for
the&lt;br /&gt;
email address domain part. So we can do our check for example as:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; spf.check2(&amp;#39;180.73.166.174&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;someone@gmail.com&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;gmail.com&amp;#39;)
(&amp;#39;neutral&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;access neither permitted nor denied&amp;#39;)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The return value would be in form &lt;code&gt;result, explanation&lt;/code&gt; which is a
tuple. &lt;code&gt;result&lt;/code&gt; can either be 'pass', 'fail', 'permerror', 'temperror',
'softfail', 'none' or 'neutral'. We run side by side test with our
existing spf function&lt;br /&gt;
and the result seem to match so we're quite confident this function is
what&lt;br /&gt;
we're looking for. Now it less one C code that we have to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="dns"></category><category term="email"></category><category term="spf"></category></entry><entry><title>Django transaction.commit_manually wrapper</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/django-transactioncommit_manually-wrapper.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-08-27T09:02:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-08-27T09:02:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-08-27:en/django-transactioncommit_manually-wrapper.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I first &lt;a href="http://metaKamal%20Mustafa.blogspot.com/2011/05/django-transactioncommitmanually-mask.html"&gt;encountered this
problem&lt;/a&gt;
1 year ago and it look's like the issue still not being fixed till now.
The &lt;a href="https://code.djangoproject.com/ticket/6623"&gt;corresponding ticket&lt;/a&gt;
has been 5 years old already. When you used
&lt;code&gt;transaction.commit_manually&lt;/code&gt; decorator around your function (usually
views function), you mark that function to be executed in single
transaction but you'll manage the transaction control, whether to commit
or rollback yourself. This in contrast to another related decorator
&lt;code&gt;transaction.commit_on_success&lt;/code&gt; where django will handle the commit or
rollback depending on the function can be successfully executed or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;transaction.commit_manually&lt;/code&gt;, there's usually a case when an
exception occurred in the function uncaught causing the commit or
rollback call not reached. When django detect this (because it see the
dirty bit in the transaction object), it raise
&lt;code&gt;TransactionManagementError&lt;/code&gt; with the infamous message 'Transaction
managed block ended with pending COMMIT/ROLLBACK'. The original
exception however is buried inside the traceback and you have to dig it
out in the order to find out the real issue. It's really annoying
because sometime you have to disable the decorator in order to find out
the real error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the issue get fixed and we manage to upgrade to latest version of
django (which unlikely to happen in the near future), I have decided to
create a wrapper around &lt;code&gt;transaction.commit_manually&lt;/code&gt; and use it instead
of the original decorator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also update the patch in the
&lt;a href="https://code.djangoproject.com/ticket/6623"&gt;ticket&lt;/a&gt; to apply cleanly to
current django trunk but so far no feedback yet from django core
developers.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="django"></category></entry><entry><title>Database Transaction in Django</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/database-transaction-in-django.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-06-21T07:54:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-06-21T07:54:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-06-21:en/database-transaction-in-django.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Keep forgetting about this so this is to wrap my heads around it. First
I have&lt;br /&gt;
the impression that Django by default execute database operations within
a&lt;br /&gt;
transaction block, which is the source of my confusion. It's true only
to&lt;br /&gt;
certain extent. The &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.3/topics/db/transactions/"&gt;first section in django
documentation&lt;/a&gt;
already explained&lt;br /&gt;
this (emphasized is mine):-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Django’s default behavior is to run with an open transaction which it&lt;br /&gt;
commits automatically when any built-in, &lt;strong&gt;data-altering model
function&lt;br /&gt;
is called&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, if you call model.save() or
model.delete(),the&lt;br /&gt;
change will be committed immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you call any function that will alter the data such as &lt;code&gt;.save()&lt;/code&gt;
method,&lt;br /&gt;
Django will commit the transaction and start a new one. Take the
following code&lt;br /&gt;
for example:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;def step1():
mms = MMSMessage()
mms.save()
step2()
@transaction.commit_manually
def step2():
transaction.rollback()
step1()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I thought no &lt;code&gt;MMSMessage&lt;/code&gt; object will be saved since when &lt;code&gt;step2()&lt;/code&gt;
function&lt;br /&gt;
get called, the transaction was rollback. But the fact is, the
transaction&lt;br /&gt;
already committed when &lt;code&gt;mms.save()&lt;/code&gt; is called and by the time &lt;code&gt;step2()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
executed it's already running in a new transaction, so the rollback does
not&lt;br /&gt;
has any effect. To get what we want, both function must be made to run
in a&lt;br /&gt;
single transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;def step1():
mms = MMSMessage()
mms.save()
step2()
@transaction.commit_manually
def step2():
transaction.rollback()
@transaction.commit_manually
def main():
step1()
main()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="django"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="transaction"></category></entry><entry><title>PyCon APAC 2012</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/pycon-apac-2012.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-06-12T20:12:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-06-12T20:12:00+09:00</updated><author><name>xoxzoblog</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-06-12:en/pycon-apac-2012.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;PyCon APAC 2012 that was held on June 7th - 9th is over. Attended by all
kinds of people from many parts of the world. It was a lovely and an eye
opening experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="asset-img-link" href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/ff4e8-6a0153916e707f970b0167676601ea970b-pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="IMG00356" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/ff4e8-6a0153916e707f970b0167676601ea970b-pi.jpg" title="IMG00356" /&gt;{.asset
.asset-image .at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b0167676601ea970b
.image-full}&lt;/a&gt;The
Marimore team attended the conference and gave a few talk (lightning
talk included) on various topics. Kamal gave a talk titled Python/Django
for PHP Developers which cause quite a stir among the attendees as two
language should never be discussed in the same room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave a brief talk on HTML5 Polyfills. It is my first talk to a public
audience accompanied by some difficulties with LibreOffice Impress
(which does not seem to want to maximize to full screen). Nevertheless
its quite an experience and there will always be a room for
improvement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="asset-img-link" href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/01c8b-6a0153916e707f970b0176155b84da970c-pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="IMG00358" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/01c8b-6a0153916e707f970b0176155b84da970c-pi.jpg" title="IMG00358" /&gt;{.asset
.asset-image .at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b0176155b84da970c
.image-full}&lt;/a&gt;Most
of the talks are great, but a few that really interest me is Diversity
as a Dependency (Anna Ravenscroft), Relational Database Access with
Python 'sans' ORM (Mark Rees). I've attended Mr Rees's talk on several
occasions, &lt;a href="http://blog.mosc.my/2009/06/testing-web-apps-with-scripting.html"&gt;MOSC
2009&lt;/a&gt;
 and other MyOSS Meetup at Technology Park Malaysia, he's an excellent
speaker and the topic he presents is kind of refreshing in a world where
framework is abundant, going back to its roots, Python DB API. Diversity
as a Dependency touched on a lot of psychological phenomenon on what
makes a group of people outstanding. The barriers that we face in
working as a group such as groupthink, conformity, anchoring and many
more are mentioned and explained in detail by the speaker, Anna
Ravenscroft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the talks are great especially the keynotes, the food is nice
and to top it off, the programming tournament is something that I have
never experienced, as I have never been good at a very time constrained
programming challenge, it was tough, me and several others only managed
to solve 1 question in 10 minutes (1st place answers all 10 questions in
that amount of time). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully on the next PyCon, it could be better with more interesting
topics and speakers, and more food delicious food of course.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Django: Where does settings belong ?</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/django-where-does-settings-belong.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-23T20:07:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-05-23T20:07:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-05-23:en/django-where-does-settings-belong.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Settings is very central to all Django applications. Django even barf if
you&lt;br /&gt;
don't supply one and import any django modules or functions (most of
it). The&lt;br /&gt;
way to specify settings to Django app however a bit awkward. Rather
calling&lt;br /&gt;
some function and pass the settings to that function, Django require you
to put&lt;br /&gt;
the path to settings module in os.environ dict. Consider a Flask
application:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;flask&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Flask&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;app&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Flask&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;__name__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nd"&gt;@app.route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;hello_world&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Hello World!&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;__name__&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;__main__&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It feels natural. You instantiate an app, call it's run() method and
pass&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;debug&lt;/code&gt; as parameter to the function. It's easy to explain. Or if Flask
not&lt;br /&gt;
your favourite, let's take a look at Bottle example:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;bottle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nd"&gt;@route&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;/hello&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;hello&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Hello World!&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;host&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;localhost&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;8080&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;debug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It still maintain the same flow. But let's look at how we pass settings
to&lt;br /&gt;
Django app. This is what you get in default &lt;code&gt;manage.py&lt;/code&gt; generated by&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;django-admin.py startproject&lt;/code&gt; command:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;environ&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;setdefault&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;DJANGO_SETTINGS_MODULE&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;myapp.settings&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;__name__&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;__main__&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;django.core.management&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;execute_from_command_line&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;execute_from_command_line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Compared to example for other 2 frameworks, the logic now seem to branch
into 2&lt;br /&gt;
separate paths. First you have to figure out what is going on with&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;os.environ.setdefault()&lt;/code&gt; stuff, and then the stuff with&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;execute_from_command_line()&lt;/code&gt;. Enough to confuse beginner. Only later on
I&lt;br /&gt;
figured out that you can actually skip &lt;code&gt;os.environ&lt;/code&gt; stuff and directly
set&lt;br /&gt;
settings as you wish. The above example can be re-written as:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;django.conf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;settings&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;settings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;configure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;DEBUG&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;__name__&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;__main__&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;django.core.management&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;execute_from_command_line&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;execute_from_command_line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now it look more like the other 2 frameworks. This however not much an
issue,&lt;br /&gt;
because once your application grow, you'll definitely want to put your
settings&lt;br /&gt;
in one central place and could be the reason why Django has made that
decision&lt;br /&gt;
for you early on. The real issue is where should we put the central
settings ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Django settings, being a pure python module mean it has to be somewhere
on your&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;sys.path&lt;/code&gt; so Django can import it to initialize the application.
Logically I&lt;br /&gt;
want the settings for &lt;code&gt;myapp&lt;/code&gt; to appear as &lt;code&gt;myapp.settings&lt;/code&gt;. This
however would&lt;br /&gt;
make the settings now part of the application. But settings suppose to
have&lt;br /&gt;
some piece of information that will be used to create and initialized
the&lt;br /&gt;
application (ROOT_URLCONF come to mind) but now the settings itself
already&lt;br /&gt;
part of the application. I've repeated the word application too much in
last&lt;br /&gt;
sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One situation when this chicken-and-egg manifest. I want to deploy my
app using&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt; which mean &lt;code&gt;myapp&lt;/code&gt; will be installed in &lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt;. That
also&lt;br /&gt;
mean &lt;code&gt;settings.py&lt;/code&gt; will also reside in &lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt;. But for web
application&lt;br /&gt;
there are more than just python code. There should be a directory to
store&lt;br /&gt;
uploaded files or csv files for some external data. I want to keep all
this in&lt;br /&gt;
a self contained project directory but since now &lt;code&gt;myapp.settings&lt;/code&gt; reside
in&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt; I'm losing the ability to calculate the path to my
project dir&lt;br /&gt;
at run time. While I can compensate this by having a standardized
location on&lt;br /&gt;
production machine, I'd still want to keep this in one single project
dir for&lt;br /&gt;
development so each developers work doesn't step into each other and
also for&lt;br /&gt;
portabilty of development environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way now is to not installing &lt;code&gt;myapp&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt; but
altering&lt;br /&gt;
sys.path to add path to the directory containing &lt;code&gt;myapp&lt;/code&gt; package. Some
of open&lt;br /&gt;
source django project I found put &lt;code&gt;settings.py&lt;/code&gt; outside the app
packages,&lt;br /&gt;
usually at the same level of &lt;code&gt;manage.py&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.wsgi&lt;/code&gt; script used to
launch the&lt;br /&gt;
app. They then specify the settings as
&lt;code&gt;os.environ['DJANGO_SETTINGS_MODULE'] = 'settings'&lt;/code&gt;. This make settings
external to the application but at the same time&lt;br /&gt;
exposed &lt;code&gt;settings&lt;/code&gt; into the global namespace. While I haven't yet found
any&lt;br /&gt;
packages at PyPI using the name &lt;code&gt;settings&lt;/code&gt;, it still doesn't feel right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take a look at how settings are handled in Pylons/Pyramid project. Few
things&lt;br /&gt;
observed:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use INI files instead of pure python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The INI files are placed at the top level of project directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application get installed into &lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt; using setup.py&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since settings stayed in project dir, you still get referenced to
    the project&lt;br /&gt;
   dir even your app get installed into &lt;code&gt;site-packages&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it look quite similar to placing &lt;code&gt;settings.py&lt;/code&gt; at your project
root, the&lt;br /&gt;
INI files is not python module so there's no problem of exposing the
settings&lt;br /&gt;
into global namespace. The settings now also look truely external to
the&lt;br /&gt;
application. This has getting quite long but still the question
remained&lt;br /&gt;
unanswered, where should we put the settings file ?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="django"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>PHP execution model vs Python web</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/php-execution-model-vs-python-web.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-02T16:48:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-05-02T16:48:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-05-02:en/php-execution-model-vs-python-web.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're still looking for a better way to explain the difference between
PHP execution model vs Python for web application to new developers
joining us. This is to help them understand the key differences when
developing web application in Python. One source of confusion among them
was when they realized the state-full nature of Python web application
compared to state-less nature of PHP. The following diagram is my
attempt to show them these key difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PHP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;

[![Php](https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/5e422-6a0153916e707f970b0168eaaad5df970c-pi.png?w=271 "Php"){.asset
.asset-image
.at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b0168eaaad5df970c}](https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/5e422-6a0153916e707f970b0168eaaad5df970c-pi.png){.asset-img-link}

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PHP execution model is quite simple actually and follow a cgi-like
model. It simply take the php file as it's input, parse and interpret it
and then return what ever output the script produced, pass it back to
apache as response that will return back to requesting user (browser).
Unlike cgi, mod_php already preloaded with the PHP interpreter so the
process of parsing and executing the script is fast since it does not
need to invoke PHP interpreter for each requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This diagram also tell us that &lt;code&gt;mod_php&lt;/code&gt; is simply a fast PHP
interpreter and it does not know anything about our application. This
make PHP a state-less environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;

[![Python](https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/7c5e7-6a0153916e707f970b016765b4178f970b-pi.png?w=216 "Python"){.asset
.asset-image
.at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b016765b4178f970b}](https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/7c5e7-6a0153916e707f970b016765b4178f970b-pi.png){.asset-img-link}

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Python/Django execution model, our app always running as part of the
server process (although probably as separate user) and only the views
function/callable that will be executed on each request. This mean some
part of our code will only been executed once when we start/restart the
web server and only the code in the views function/callable are
guaranteed to run in each requests. This mean it's possible to store
data that would persist between requests. For example:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;django.http&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;HttpResponse&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;counter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;home&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;request&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;counter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;HttpResponse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Counter: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;counter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is simple django views and if you access this through browser
you'll see the counter value will be incremented every time you refresh
the browser. If you're just coming from PHP this new fact should be more
a warning than a cool new thing you want to try doing since most of the
time you want to avoid storing state like this and make sure you always
start with a fresh data on each requests. If you really need to store
data that persist between requests such remembering user already login,
there's better way such as django session object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important consequences from this new fact about python execution
model is that it mean when we change our code, we have to restart the
server so that it will have the latest copy of our code. PHP programmers
might found this daunting at first but if you already work in
application server model like Java you'll know that this is rather
typical because when the server is start, it already load our code into
memory, waiting to call some function when request came in. PHP due to
it's CGI-like manner is different because the whole code only executed
as part of the request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Executing whole application code on each requests work best with PHP
because it's already been designed from the ground up as web language.
The standard library functions in PHP also been written in C so it's
already fast and executing that on each requests doesn't matter much.
Python however has most of it's standard library written in Python
itself which mean executing that on each request would be too slow.
You'll also facing the same problem in PHP once your code base grow to
certain level where you need to look for solution that cache the opcode
such as APC or eAccelerator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely there are more to discuss on the differences between PHP and
Python execution model for web application but I hope this post can
start giving you an idea why developing in Python a bit different than
what you already accustomed to in PHP. I'll try to expand this topic
more in upcoming posts and also welcome any suggestion to help PHP
developers to keep up fast in Python web development. Related reading
that help me a lot in understanding the difference between PHP and
Python web execution model is a blog post by Ian Bicking few years ago -
&lt;a href="http://blog.ianbicking.org/2008/01/12/what-php-deployment-gets-right/"&gt;What PHP Deployment Gets
Right&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="php"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>Supporting HTML5 features in browsers using polyfill</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/polyfilling-the-future.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-04-23T11:23:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-04-23T11:23:00+09:00</updated><author><name>xoxzoblog</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-04-23:en/polyfilling-the-future.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;

**What is polyfill?**

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

A polyfill or polyfiller is code designed to provide technology that is
not native to a web browser. For example, earlier versions of Internet
Explorer do not support all the features of HTML5 which may necessitate
the use of polyfills to display features of HTML5 which are not
supported by the web browser.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

**What does it mean?**

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

If you use &amp;lt;audio&amp;gt; tag for certain filetypes (for example, an mp3
file), there are some browser that do not supports it.[^\[1\]^](anchor1)
What does it needs to be done if we want to play an mp3 file on Firefox
3.6? Well, we can use a flash audio player for instance or we could
provide other compatible files. The latter is not preferable for it
requires a lot of space and processing power. We'd have to convert every
single file that are not supported by browsers to a format it supports.
Polyfills provide a fallback for this type of
situations.[^\[2\]^](anchor2)

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

**How Do We Check A Feature Is In A Browser?**

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

Check out &lt;http://html5readiness.com/&gt; to view the readiness of a
browser to a specific HTML5 feature. 

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="asset-img-link" href="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/860d2-6a0153916e707f970b0168ea921382970c-pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Capture4-23-2012-6.41.10
AM" src="https://xoxzoblog.files.wordpress.com/2012/04/860d2-6a0153916e707f970b0168ea921382970c-pi.jpg" title="Capture4-23-2012-6.41.10 AM" /&gt;{.asset
.asset-image .at-xid-6a0153916e707f970b0168ea921382970c
.image-full}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

**But How Do We Check It In Code?**

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

To check it in code, we could use Modernizr to detect if a specific
feature is in the browser. &lt;http://modernizr.com/docs/#features-css&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

For example,

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;if (Modernizr.audio.mp3 == &amp;#39;&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;&amp;#39; == false)
{
// Use the flash audio player
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div&gt;

**Where Do We Get These Polyfills?**

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

Most of them are listed at &lt;http://html5please.com&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

**That's it. **

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

The "polyfill" or "regressive enhancement" technique just means that you
go ahead and use HTML5 features then use other libraries to emulate
native behavior in older browsers. So instead of worrying about support
in some browsers, use these polyfills to enhance the browsers to provide
the user with proper experience to your web sites and applications.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

[1.]( "anchor1") &lt;http://html5doctor.com/native-audio-in-the-browser/&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;

[2.]( "anchor2") &lt;http://html5please.com/#audio&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Releasing dev version of your package to PyPI</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/releasing-dev-version-of-your-package-to-pypi.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-03-20T08:50:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-03-20T08:50:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-03-20:en/releasing-dev-version-of-your-package-to-pypi.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt; (Python Package Index) has become a
central place for python developers these days to look for third party
libraries. Common tools such as easy_install, pip or buildout by
default will look into &lt;a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt; when asked to
install certain packages. For example:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;easy_install Django
easy_install Django==1.3.1
pip install Django
pip install Django==1.2.4
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;all those commands above will either install the latest stable release
of Django or an exact version as specified as argument to the command.
For our own &lt;a href="https://github.com/marimore/mamopublic"&gt;mamopublic&lt;/a&gt;
package, I'd plan to also release it on
&lt;a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt; so it more inline with other third
party libraries that we need to install as part of our project
dependencies. The process actually pretty straightforward, once you have
sign up and get your username and password, all you have to do is from
your package root:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;python setup.py register # this will register the package name on pypi
python setup.py sdist upload
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It will ask you to save the username and password in &lt;code&gt;~/.pypirc&lt;/code&gt; so you
don't have to&lt;br /&gt;
type username and password everytime you want to upload to
&lt;a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt;. Now I can install
&lt;a href="https://github.com/marimore/mamopublic"&gt;mamopublic&lt;/a&gt; simpy by just
typing &lt;code&gt;easy_install mamopublic&lt;/code&gt;. That will grab the tarball from
&lt;a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt; website. There's always a case that
I want to install the latest code from our github commit. I have seen
lot of packages on &lt;a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt; that allow us to
install their latest dev release using command such as:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;easy_install django-nose==dev
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking around in setuptools/distribute documentation, I didn't found
any settings for &lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt; that allow us to specify the url to download
the package instead from &lt;a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi"&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt;'s tarball.
Finally, checking package edit page on PyPI I noticed that there's an
input field for download url. So what I did was to change the version in
setup.py to 'dev' instead of '1.8' and then upload it to PyPI. Since
'dev' version not exists yet, PyPI happily accept that. PyPI apparently
refused to accept upload of package of similar version. You have to bump
the version number or delete the package from PyPI first. Then I went to
the package edit page and specified the download url pointing to github
generated tarball from latest commit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it's possible to install our latest commit simply by using
&lt;code&gt;easy_install -U mamopublic==dev&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="distribute"></category><category term="easy_install"></category><category term="pip"></category><category term="pypi"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="setuptools"></category></entry><entry><title>Svn stash</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/svn-stash.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-03-09T19:32:00+09:00</published><updated>2012-03-09T19:32:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2012-03-09:en/svn-stash.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Update 2012-05-02 - Add new use-case when merging from trunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I like in git is the &lt;code&gt;stash&lt;/code&gt; command. Basically what it's
doing is&lt;br /&gt;
to take out current changes that we have, store it in temporary place
and then&lt;br /&gt;
revert our repo to it's previous pristine state. This has a number of
use cases.&lt;br /&gt;
Let say you're working on some features and then got some bug report
that need&lt;br /&gt;
to be fixed quickly. You may do new checkout in other location and do
the bug&lt;br /&gt;
fixing work, commit it and then continue on your new features work. This
may not&lt;br /&gt;
really prevalent if you work in branch since the bug might need to be
fixed in&lt;br /&gt;
another branch. &lt;code&gt;git branch&lt;/code&gt; does the job here since it allow you to
quickly&lt;br /&gt;
switch branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now back to us who still stuck with svn. Nothing wrong with svn, it does
the work&lt;br /&gt;
and 99% of the time we're happy with it. There's another use case than I
mentioned&lt;br /&gt;
just now. Supposed while working on the new features, you found a bug.
It may be&lt;br /&gt;
just 1 line fix and you don't want the fix end up with features you're
working on&lt;br /&gt;
currently. With svn, you have few options:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do new checkout in another directory, fix the bug and commit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;svn diff &amp;gt; tmp.diff&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;svn revert -R .&lt;/code&gt;, fix the bug and commit,
    &lt;code&gt;patch -p0 &amp;lt; tmp.diff&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second option not really nice solution if you have lot of newly added
files and&lt;br /&gt;
you want to have clean environment in order to test the bug fixes. You
have to&lt;br /&gt;
manually copy all the files to some other place. So I search around for
'svn stash'&lt;br /&gt;
and luckily there's few others who'd also thinking about 'svn stash'.
&lt;a href="http://www.blisted.org/blog/bin/svn/stash"&gt;There's one&lt;br /&gt;
that look complete&lt;/a&gt;, from a
guy named scott (can't find any more details) so I&lt;br /&gt;
give it a try. The script work quite well, it named as &lt;code&gt;svn&lt;/code&gt;, just put
somewhere&lt;br /&gt;
under your &lt;code&gt;$PATH&lt;/code&gt;, make sure it come first before the usual path such
as &lt;code&gt;/usr/bin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
or &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin&lt;/code&gt;. The script basically a wrapper to actually svn
executable,&lt;br /&gt;
it contains few additonal commands and if none match, it just forward
that to the real svn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott's blog have enough explanation on how to use the script so I won't
repeat it&lt;br /&gt;
here. Basically the flow are:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;svn stash&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... fix bug etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;svn commit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;svn stash list&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;svn stash pop&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;svn stash apply &amp;lt;stash-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; - pop will remove
    the stash while &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; will keep it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another useful use-case is when working on branch. While in the middle
of your work on the branch, you might want to merge latest changes from
trunk. It always good practice to merge into a clean working directory
rather than have the changes from merge mix your current uncommitted
work. You may not ready yet to commit your current changes. With &lt;code&gt;stash&lt;/code&gt;
command you can 'stash' the current changes, merge latest changes from
trunk, commit, reapply the stash and continue to work:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;kamal@sms:~/marimore_sms/branches/381-reset-count
$ svn status
M       lib/py/mamoprivate/sms/__init__.py
M       bin/sendsmsd
kamal@sms:~/marimore_sms/branches/381-reset-count
$ svn stash
Reverted &amp;#39;lib/py/mamoprivate/sms/__init__.py&amp;#39;
Reverted &amp;#39;bin/sendsmsd&amp;#39;
Changes stashed as: &amp;quot;4d51a3eb-3a16-4e63-89e7-09e74cd30d91&amp;quot;
Working copy reverted to 129
kamal@sms:~/marimore_sms/branches/381-reset-count
$ svn status
kamal@sms:~/marimore_sms/branches/381-reset-count
$ svn merge ../../trunk/
--- Merging r129 through r132 into &amp;#39;.&amp;#39;:
U    lib/py/mamoprivate/d/projects/sms/settings.py
M       lib/py/mamoprivate/d/projects/sms/settings.py
kamal@sms:~/marimore_sms/branches/381-reset-count
$ svn ci -m &amp;#39;merge latest trunk, refs #381&amp;#39;
Sending        381-reset-count
Sending        381-reset-count/lib/py/mamoprivate/d/projects/sms/settings.py
Transmitting file data .
Committed revision 133.
kamal@sms:~/marimore_sms/branches/381-reset-count
$ svn stash list
1637 2012-05-02 13:56 4d51a3eb-3a16-4e63-89e7-09e74cd30d91
kamal@sms:~/marimore_sms/branches/381-reset-count
$ svn stash pop 4d51a3eb-3a16-4e63-89e7-09e74cd30d91
pop: 4d51a3eb-3a16-4e63-89e7-09e74cd30d91
Unstaging stash &amp;quot;4d51a3eb-3a16-4e63-89e7-09e74cd30d91&amp;quot;.
M       lib/py/mamoprivate/sms/__init__.py
M       bin/sendsmsd
Stash &amp;quot;4d51a3eb-3a16-4e63-89e7-09e74cd30d91&amp;quot; removed.
kamal@sms:~/marimore_sms/branches/381-reset-count
$ svn status
M       lib/py/mamoprivate/sms/__init__.py
M       bin/sendsmsd
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It also have some other goodies but I haven't try any of them. The
script also show&lt;br /&gt;
a creative way to provide 'plugins' to a command that do not natively
support plugin.&lt;br /&gt;
I might apply the same technique to other command. I have in mind to
override the&lt;br /&gt;
svn commit command to provide some kind pre-commit hook that run the
code through&lt;br /&gt;
static code checker before commiting. We're using Unfuddle so no chance
for us to use&lt;br /&gt;
the native svn pre-commit hook. Lastly, thanks to
&lt;a href="http://www.blisted.org/"&gt;scott&lt;/a&gt; for such useful script.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="git"></category><category term="svn"></category><category term="version control"></category></entry><entry><title>Understanding Python Import</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/understanding-python-import.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-11-22T16:32:00+09:00</published><updated>2011-11-22T16:32:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2011-11-22:en/understanding-python-import.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There's a lot have been written on understanding Python import so I'm
not sure whether this one would help to clear the confusion or just add
more. I hope for the former. Having a new hire who is new to Python
bring up this issue again for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python has few ways to import other modules and has been greatly covered
in effbot's article - &lt;a href="http://effbot.org/zone/import-confusion.htm"&gt;Importing Python
Modules&lt;/a&gt;. Module in Python
is any file that end with .py. You can import it if you can somehow make
that file available on Python import path (more on this later). An
immediate companion to module is package - you can think of it as
collection of modules but there's much simpler definition - any
directory containing (even blank) file named as &lt;code&gt;__init__.py&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the first form of import in python which is the &lt;code&gt;import&lt;/code&gt; statement
can only import a module or package. Let say we have this example module
named &lt;code&gt;sugar&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;touch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sugar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;python&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Python&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;2.6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;r265&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;79063&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Apr&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;16&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2010&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;56&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;GCC&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;4.4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;linux2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;help&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;copyright&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;credits&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;license&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;more&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;information&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sugar&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sugar&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That's quite clear I think. We have file named &lt;code&gt;sugar.py&lt;/code&gt; and then we
can import it from python interpreter executed within the same
directory. If there's a function named &lt;code&gt;is_sweet()&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;sugar.py&lt;/code&gt;, we
can reference it now as &lt;code&gt;sugar.is_sweet()&lt;/code&gt;. Following this, you might be
attempting to do the following:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sugar.is_sweet&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Traceback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;most&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;recent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;console&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;ImportError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;No&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;named&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;is_sweet&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the error message say, there's no module name is_sweet. Remember, we
can only import module (or package) ? &lt;code&gt;is_sweet&lt;/code&gt; on the other hand is a
function so I hope this is pretty clear at this moment. There could be
few reasons why you want to import only specific object rather than the
whole module and since python doesn't allow this, is this the end of the
world ? Luckily python provide another form of import that is
&lt;code&gt;from ... import&lt;/code&gt; or I prefer to illustrate it as
&lt;code&gt;from module|package import object&lt;/code&gt;. So, continuing from previous
example:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sugar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;is_sweet&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;is_sweet&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;is_sweet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mh"&gt;0xb731de9c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now we can import &lt;code&gt;is_sweet&lt;/code&gt; function from module &lt;code&gt;sugar&lt;/code&gt;. So we can
import specific object from a module using
&lt;code&gt;from module|package import object&lt;/code&gt; form. Noticed that I used the term
object here because in python everything is an object - module is
object, package is object, function is object, class is object etc. Let
say we reorganize our sugar module into a package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ mkdir sugar
$ touch sugar/__init__.py
$ touch sugar/white.py
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here we added new module named &lt;code&gt;white&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;sugar&lt;/code&gt; package. To
specifically import white module we can:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sugar.white&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sugar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;white&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;sugar.white&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;sugar/white.pyc&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;or:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sugar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;white&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;white&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;sugar.white&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;sugar/white.pyc&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Try to say this phrase again in your head for a few times -
&lt;code&gt;from module|package import object&lt;/code&gt; - (In English - from a module or
package, you can import an object). Again, everything is object in
Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Import path&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we understand how import work (hopefully), another question come up.
How does python know where to look for all these modules ? When trying
to import module, Python look through a list of path. This list is
stored under &lt;code&gt;sys&lt;/code&gt; module and can be referenced as &lt;code&gt;sys.path&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;/home/kamal/lib/python2.6/site-packages/setuptools-0.6c11-py2.6.egg&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;/home/kamal/lib/python2.6/site-packages/pip-1.0.1-py2.6.egg&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;/home/kamal/lib/python2.6/site-packages/patu-0.1-py2.6.egg&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;/home/kamal/lib/python2.6/site-packages/lxml-2.3-py2.6-linux-i686.egg&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;......&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Python provide a number of ways for you to modify this list of path so
that module that you intended can be found. One of it by specifying
environment variable named PYTHONPATH.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;PYTHONPATH=/home/kamal/my-python-lib
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From now on, any &lt;code&gt;*.py&lt;/code&gt; file under &lt;code&gt;/home/kamal/my-python-lib&lt;/code&gt; can be
imported if you execute python from that environment. Another way is to
modify &lt;code&gt;sys.path&lt;/code&gt; directly and more convenient since you can do this in
the initial bootstrap code of your application.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>Subversion merging changes between branches</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/subversion-merging-changes-between-branches.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-09-24T08:04:00+09:00</published><updated>2011-09-24T08:04:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2011-09-24:en/subversion-merging-changes-between-branches.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For svn branching strategy, we used the &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/597707/best-branching-strategy-when-doing-continuous-integration"&gt;feature
branch&lt;/a&gt;
approach. This mean we keep trunk stable at all time and for any new
features to work on, we start a new branch. While working on the branch,
we'll keep it in sync with trunk by merging any latest changes happened
on the trunk. Once the feature is ready, we merge that branch back into
trunk. Subversion &amp;gt; 1.5 &lt;code&gt;--reintegrate&lt;/code&gt; option really helpfull here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a case however we end up with multiple branches active at a
time. Supposed there are 3 new features that need to be implemented.
Logically I would start 3 separate branches to work on each features
since all of it are not related to each other. Let assume I start 3
branches named as branch-A, branch-B and branch-C. I keep working on
these 3 branches over the time. As the time passed by, branch-A is
finished and ready to get into trunk. As usual after making sure
branch-A has all the latest changes in trunk, I merged it back into
trunk:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; branches/branch-A
$ svn merge ../../trunk
$ svn ci -m &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;merge latest changes from trunk into branch-A&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
$ &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ../../trunk
$ svn merge --reintegrate ../branches/branch-A
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Everything work flawlessly and as expected here. Before continuing
working on other branches, I'll make sure all those branches in sync
with trunk by merging all latest changes in the trunk. This would
include the new features implemented in branch-A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; branches/branch-B
$ svn merge ../../trunk
$ svn ci -m &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;merge latest trunk into branch-B&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
$ &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; branches/branch-C
$ svn merge ../../trunk
$ svn ci -m &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;merge latest trunk into branch-C&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'd then continue working on branch-B and branch-C. Later on I'd
realized that changes that I made in branch-C actually also needed in
branch-B. Let assume I added new function in branch-C and then found out
that the code in branch-B also need the same function. Now it's not
possible to merge branch-C into trunk yet so that it changes can be
propagated to branch-B. Ideally I should be able to merge changes
between branch-B and branch-C before merging back both branches into
trunk but subversion is not that clever in tracking merge between
branches like this. So I decided that all development now should be done
in branch-B. This mean I need to merge all changes that been done in
branch-C into branch-B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When trying to do this - merge branch-C into branch-B, I ended up with
lot of conflict. Remember the changes we have done in the branch-A
earlier ? In branch-A, among the changes that we have done involved
adding some new files. Now the changes (adding new files) exists in both
branch-B and branch-C because we take it from trunk. When merging
branch-C into branch-B subversion will try to add the new files again
and we have conflict. It said something like - "local add, incoming add
upon merge". Searching around, I found the solution in this &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/738367/why-am-i-getting-tree-conflicts-in-subversion"&gt;SO
question&lt;/a&gt;:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ svn resolve -R --accept working
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It mean for any conflict, keep the current working copy and discard the
incoming changes. This is fine if you know exactly the changes that you
need contained in different files than the conflicted one. Otherwise you
have to manually inspect the file and fix the conflicting line. I'm not
sure yet whether this can be merged cleanly back to the trunk. Will
update this post later.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scm"></category><category term="subversion"></category><category term="svn"></category><category term="version control"></category></entry><entry><title>Vacancy: Full-time Junior Python/Django Web Developer</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/vacancy-junior-pythondjango-web-developer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-09-19T08:09:00+09:00</published><updated>2011-09-19T08:09:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2011-09-19:en/vacancy-junior-pythondjango-web-developer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;MARIMORE ENGINEERING SDN. BHD. develops and maintains Django/Python
based web applications for our clients. We rely heavily on open source
and at the same time try to contribute back to the community via open
source code, documentation, monetary contribution or participation in
open source events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe in ROWE (Results Only Work Environment). All our members are
given a high level of freedom, in exchange for a high level of
dedication and responsibility towards their art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop new features for services provided by Marimore Inc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Services include sms sending API, forum sites and content based
    web applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintain existing features and do timely update to the software and
    libraries used in the application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintain and write documentation for services provided and also
    internal technical documentation (wiki).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deploy new features or changes to the live server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Report your work progress and any relevant issues to the Lead
    Engineer/Engineering team on a regular basis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 to 2 years experience in web development regardless of whether as
    professional or hobbyist project. Fresh grads with good portfolio or
    open source projects also fine, please provide link to code samples
    or your project repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know HTML, CSS and basic understanding of JavaScript.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand HTTP - know at least a few common HTTP methods and how
    they are used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not fearful of the command line, be it linux/unix or windows OS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proficient in either PHP, .NET, Java, Ruby or Perl. You'll have to
    learn Python once coming on board though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL or PostgreSQL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know how to use Google.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proficient in English.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Plus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python/Django or any other framework/libraries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active in community - open source projects, forum, q&amp;amp;a sites,
    mailing list etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informative technical blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience in Amazon Web Services, esp. EC2 and RDS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expected starting salary will be MYR 2300. This will change depending on
your experience and current salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is remote position so applicant location doesn't really matter as&lt;br /&gt;
long as you have good Internet connectivity. 1 month on-site training&lt;br /&gt;
however required before you can start working from any of your&lt;br /&gt;
preferred location. Communication done through Skype, email and task&lt;br /&gt;
tracker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, we are happy to talk to you. Please contact
hr@marimore.co.jp with a copy of your CV and a short introduction about
yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align:center;"&gt;

**----- UPDATE 2011-10-07 -----**

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce that we've found some great candidates and that
&lt;strong&gt;this vacancy is now closed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your interest in MARIMORE ENGINEERING.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="developer"></category><category term="django"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="vacancy"></category></entry><entry><title>Porting function based generic views to class based views</title><link href="http://devblog.xoxzo.com/en/porting-function-based-generic-views-to-class-based-views.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-09-16T12:12:00+09:00</published><updated>2011-09-16T12:12:00+09:00</updated><author><name>Kamal Mustafa</name></author><id>tag:devblog.xoxzo.com,2011-09-16:en/porting-function-based-generic-views-to-class-based-views.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It not really obvious in the
&lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.3/ref/class-based-views/"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;
how we should proceed. I try to make as little changes as possible to
code. The following is a sample function that we need to port to class
based views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;django.views.generic&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;list_detail&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;supported_sending_networks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;request&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;page&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;django.core.paginator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Paginator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;InvalidPage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;EmptyPage&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;_TEMPLATE_PATH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;faq/list_sending_networks.html&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;network_list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;EZSPossibleSendNetwork&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;objects&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;paginator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Paginator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;network_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;list_detail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;object_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;request&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;queryset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;network_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;paginate_by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;page&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;page&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;template_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_TEMPLATE_PATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;template_object_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;networks&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The new equivalent class based views for this is
&lt;code&gt;django.views.generic.list.ListView&lt;/code&gt;. My first attempt after looking at
the documentation:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;def def supported_sending_networks(request, page=1):
class SupportedSendingNetworkView(ListView):
queryset = EZSPossibleSendNetwork.objects.all()
paginate_by = 15
context_object_name = &amp;#39;networks_list&amp;#39;
template_name = &amp;quot;faq/list_sending_networks.html&amp;quot;
return SupportedSendingNetworkView.as_view()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;but I got error related to something 'function object not iterable ...'.
Look like the as_view() function call actually return a function object
rather than a response. Looking around I'm supposed to alias the class
with the function name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;SupportedSendingNetworkView&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class="n"&gt;ListView&lt;/span&gt;):
&lt;span class="n"&gt;queryset&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="n"&gt;EZSPossibleSendNetwork&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class="n"&gt;objects&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class="nb"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt;()
&lt;span class="n"&gt;paginate_by&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;context_object_name&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;networks_list&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;template_name&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;faq/list_sending_networks.html&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;supported_sending_networks&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="n"&gt;SupportedSendingNetworkView&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class="n"&gt;as_view&lt;/span&gt;()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Make sense since now &lt;code&gt;supported_sending_networks&lt;/code&gt; would simply be a
plain function. While the views now work, there's still no pager. Turn
out that now Django only expect the &lt;code&gt;page&lt;/code&gt; parameter for the pager to
work in either two ways only:-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specified as parameter in the urlconf.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As query string parameter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This mean I have to modify my urls.py definition. Once that defined, I
need to pass the page value as a context object by overriding the
get_context_data() method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;SupportedSendingNetworkView&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class="n"&gt;ListView&lt;/span&gt;):
&lt;span class="n"&gt;queryset&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="n"&gt;EZSPossibleSendNetwork&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class="n"&gt;objects&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class="nb"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt;()
&lt;span class="n"&gt;paginate_by&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;context_object_name&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;networks_list&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;template_name&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;faq/list_sending_networks.html&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;get_context_data&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class="k"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;, **&lt;span class="n"&gt;kwargs&lt;/span&gt;):
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;context&lt;/span&gt; = &lt;span class="n"&gt;super&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class="n"&gt;SupportedSendingNetworkView&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="k"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;span class="n"&gt;get_context_data&lt;/span&gt;(**&lt;span class="n"&gt;kwargs&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;span class="n"&gt;try:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;page&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;] = &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span class="k"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class="n"&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;])
&lt;span class="n"&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class="n"&gt;IndexError&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="n"&gt;ValueError&lt;/span&gt;):
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;page&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;] = &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All parameters to the views now available as &lt;code&gt;self.args&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code&gt;self.kwargs&lt;/code&gt; respectively. Some other notes, function based generic
views would be &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/internals/deprecation/"&gt;deprecated in
Django-1.5&lt;/a&gt;
so if you moving to Django-1.3 this a good time to start porting your
generic views usage to class based views. It also not obvious to me that
we have to call the superclass method when overriding &lt;code&gt;get_context_data&lt;/code&gt;
method otherwise you would not have the complete context data. It only
after I found this blog &lt;a href="http://blog.oscarcp.com/?p=182"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="class based views"></category><category term="django"></category><category term="django views"></category><category term="generic views"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry></feed>